hello and welcome everyone
it's June 3rd 2023 we're in the first
discussion section for physics as
information processing course with Chris
fields so welcome to all who are here on
and off camera really exciting to see so
many people joining for this
participatory discussion section so in
this first interval
we're going to
go to anyone who raises their hand and
it would be awesome to hear from
everyone who'd like to share
what excites them about what they heard
in the first lecture how has their
background and journey led to them
joining what are they hoping to learn
and do
in this course
so
first hand we'll get to go
maybe Andre you can actually start first
just speaking as a normal participant
and then meanwhile anyone is welcome to
raise their hands
that sounds good so I
I am a mathematician by training
um but I've always been interested in
the more physics side of things
and in particular you know I followed
Chris's work
I'll work pretty closely since probably
uh and I don't know I'm just very
interested in the whole ontology of
quantum measurement what it means
um I feel like you know very often when
it's taught in physics classes it's hand
waved away
and even though I myself uh subscribe to
the philosophy of you know shut up and
compute
sometimes you know not everything you
need to do a little bit of philosophy
maybe and this may be one of the things
where you need to do it I usually to
address it from uh first principles
right and I think Chris is doing that so
I'm just here to learn more and yeah
that's basically it
awesome I'll just go from the top left
because I'm not necessarily watching
like what order but Ross first
hi
um
I'm interested in the kind of overlap
between cognitive science and physics
and seeing if uh there are any pan
psychist implications of the observation
that uh
physical processes seem to follow the
same kind of principle that we see apply
to uh brains and cognitive systems
awesome thank you Avo
hi I am uh I'm uh mixed backgrounds
uh mostly physics and cognitive science
right now I could be qualified as a
philosopher of
physics and cognitive science and I'm
interested in uh basically formalizing
participatorialism the idea that
Observer participate in creating reality
I did some work in formalizing that in
the case of social norms and things like
language
and I met a block based on my lack of
knowledge of quantum physics and the
mathematical tools that I used for that
so I'm here in a course to get those
formal skills
awesome thank you evil blue
I think Alex was first
okay Alexi go for it oh sorry
hi I'm Alexia I'm a clinical
psychologist in Maryland in the states I
uh work with patients do Psychotherapy
mostly my interest came through uh Mark
zolmes uh who is uh you know the Creator
and leader of neuroscycle analysis and
he has been collaborating with friston
uh on uh heart problem of Consciousness
and he's not working on AI with emotions
and so uh he you know I blame him I say
it with respect and love that for uh
introducing mathematics into our field
which was mostly devoid of mathematics
and uh people started looking at these
partial differential equations and Mark
with blankets uh so I wrote a paper
about a possible extension of their
model uh to include chaos theory and I
just want to understand deeper uh
Concepts involved I have some
understanding of them but perhaps not
enough and I'm enjoying this course a
great deal I mean I think Chris among
other things is a fantastic teacher and
he is able to express things very
clearly and it just I have oh I have
Goosebumps so I'm very grateful to
everybody and thank you so much
cool blue then Francesco
hi everyone I'm blue Knight I'm with the
active inference Institute so I've been
tracking this work of Chris's
um you know connecting Quantum
information and active inference for I
don't know a couple couple years now
through through that thread
um I'm super interested actually in
um the aspect of
space-time arising from communication I
think that that's like fascinating to
dive into and how it connects to the
like Buddhist and maybe more Eastern
religion like concept of dependent
arising like how like the
interdependence of
all things leads to their existence
um and and so from from that aspect I
think that that's like the what I'm most
interested in exploring my background is
um Neuroscience but I've also been
studying practicing Buddhism for like 25
years so
um yeah that's it thanks
awesome Francesco then Corby
thanks Daniel ciao everyone super happy
to be here I also have a mixed
background because I studied cognitive
anthropology and philosophy of science
and currently a few months ago I started
a PhD in artificial intelligence in an
es application in the educational field
and yes I'm actually super excited about
the all the science implications that
Chris Fields mentioned in the first
lecture in connection I have no
background in physics but the
connections between the first principles
of physics and free energy principle and
scientific condition in general is what
is really getting me excited in these
days thank you
cool Corby then anyone else who raises
their hint
uh yeah great to be here
um my background is in Quantum
engineering uh I've always been
motivated by figuring out what the next
big thing in Computing was in high
school Morris law was sort of coming to
an end and it seemed like a really big
opportunity to figure out what the next
big Computing architecture might be so I
did academic research and no more for
computing Quantum Computing and Quantum
sensors and I felt like I was a little
bit too early for all of those things so
I went into uh cloud and cloud gaming
and streaming AI services but I'm still
extremely motivated to figure out what
the next big thing is in the holographic
principle seems like a good foundation
to explore that
awesome
I'll raise my own hand than anyone else
is uh welcome to go so I'm Daniel
I'm a researcher at The Institute and
have known under for some years and
learns about all kinds of stochastic
matrices and how the math and the
quantum were linked and we had talked
and joked about
learning from Chris fields for a long
time so when the opportunity arose to
enact it
and extend it and open it we were very
excited
and also don't have much of a formal
background in physics outside of working
with Jacob and Ali on Livestream 49.
um
so it's just going to be a great
time to learn and see where it all goes
anyone else want to say uh hello in this
kind of opening section
okay well
continuing forward of course please just
feel free to raise your hand anytime
you'd like to
jump into the stack
under for for several minutes or however
you see could you
reflect on lecture one
where did Chris enter how did he proceed
and where did the lecture take us
um
thank you
yeah so can you zoom in a little bit
more on the PDF
can you hear me thank you good go for it
let's uh take a look at the slides from
last time so I think if if we were to
summarize this
um whole lecture
basically what Chris was trying to say
is that there are many hints coming from
different directions
pointing at the same thing right
pointing at the fact that you know
information
no will have a central aspect
uh in physics in the future but also
possibly biology right so
the earliest games came from
statistical mechanics if you wish
but it also uh quantum mechanics right
again we need to make a like an
important but subtle distinction between
what it is the uncertainty principle
right because you know we think of that
as as the informational part right like
a limit on the resolution on information
uh and what is the observer effect just
to make that distinction clear I think
Chris is talking about the observer
effect the uncertainty principle is a an
artifact of the wave nature of you know
quantum mechanics right you can you can
get it from properties of the Fourier
transform with cautious Schwartz
inequality but at the end of the day
it's what I was saying earlier right
what is the basic picture of measurement
right and that's sort of increase with
glazebrook and Marciano is trying to
address
and the first two hints came from
from quantum mechanics around 1900 and
statistical mechanics a few decades
earlier
then there's you know
more stuff right like uh obviously
businesses uh resisted to inertia of
hundreds of years of a totally objective
you know
Observer independent universe but the
hints continued to pile on
um
some stuff coming from math but perhaps
the most interesting is is again you
know how all those paradoxes from
statistical mechanics were
were made sense of with Land hours
proposal
and then as physics got more fancy past
you know qft and stuff you know people
started thinking about
um
Quantum information more seriously so we
had Dell serum and all these proportions
by Deutsch and Wheeler and so on
and I and I should say that
um this is not a fringe idea in physics
uh the Paradigm of it from qubit is very
much mainstream I mean Google it a lot
of physicists
think about it you know I don't know how
many of them you know talk about it
openly but you know it's it's been a
widespread folk intuition so to speak
that you know information will have this
sort of central role
yeah and the last
sort of hints pointing in that direction
of information having a control what
came on the one side from high energy
stuff and that's the holographic
principle is
it originally arose in the context of
black hole for Dynamics but then you
know it was extended to you
to you know what's called the abs-cft
correspondence and the very most recent
stuff was you know it's Basics
on the one side from high energy staff
sorry I can't speak a little more loudly
it's all good continue honor
yeah I thought there was a question uh
someone was just unmuted it's all good
okay uh yeah so so that's basically it
right so let's there's hints
from many directions and most recently
uh you know the work of Tristan and
Levin coming from biology all pointing
in the same direction right that there
we might have to make sense of some sort
of
potentially scale free
information processing uh Peridot or for
what it means to be an observer you know
sort of all of these things are pointing
in that direction and I think Chris's
work is is addressing that head-on right
as I said earlier you know sometimes you
know it's it's good to do computations
but sometimes you need to take a step
back and think more philosophically
about what you're doing and what the
bigger picture is
and then maybe after people talk a
little bit I can you know we can warm up
to the second lecture we can the other
windows that I have open here
um some of them are the papers that are
to come
yeah anyone please feel free to
um raise your hand on this Alexia than
anyone else
well I had one uh thought about this
thing you know when you mentioned uh
that there's various perspectives from
the same concept and I'm trying to be
cautious on the one hand I think again
this amazing Clarity and precision with
which Chris expressed
um uh thoughts is is fantastic and
enjoyable on the other hand it requires
simplification and generalization and
what I observe in my field is take
people take a term like entropy and run
with it and then they get very quickly
from thermodynamic entropy to Shannon to
you know whatever entropy and they talk
about sort of
um and that's not the case I mean if we
go back to class use and all the others
there was a system of postulates and
axioms that must be maintained and if
you step outside of that so like us
organisms we're open systems we're not
closed systems so we should not apply
directly second world thermodynamics and
you know I I deal a little more with
kolmogorov's and I entropy and which is
not the same thing and I guess when we
very quickly we move from sort of
thermodynamics to you know uh to
statistical mechanics with boltzmann to
you know all the way around and we
assume it is the same thing I think we
may need to be careful because we are
just ignoring the differences in
assumptions you know Shannon talked
about Telegraph he talked about a
receiver getting a message from a sender
right and clausius talked about you know
uh gas so
um but but I do think it's a balancing
act and there's no way to not have
simplification and generalization I just
wanted to say somewhere somehow we need
to kind of you know go back there and
just say you know uh entropy is not
entropy is not entropy and all these
things are kind of you know long papers
right
yes Jakob then Ali than anyone else
um
I um
I just wanted to uh
ask for I guess perhaps uh slightly
longer comment from Alexian
that what you see as the fundamental
differences
in different descriptions of entropy and
whether there is
some
I guess General concept that could be
extracted from all of them such as level
of information or uncertainty about a
particular system even though these
specific uh formulations of entropy they
talk about they were derived from
different specific systems and they have
different equations describing them and
they mean slightly different things
do um
do you think it would be wrong to say
that there is some commonality between
them
did I answer Daniel or yeah
I don't know I just think we need to at
some point formalize it and
um and be careful with these
generalizations for example uh when we
talk about active inference and Tristan
right you know when we say living
organisms must minimize I'm quoting
first and by the way these are not my
thoughts the entropy of sensory States
right and then people take that idea
sometimes and generalize and they say
that that's what life is minimization of
entropy right but if you actually look
into a human brain and measure entropy
then it goes all over the place up down
and in between uh and so I I don't think
that's an accurate description and the
reason for that is we're we shifted away
from the uh assumptions and uh again so
comma version I entropy talks about the
phase space and the Divergence of
trajectories in face space and sort of
the volume in face space while when you
talk about this for instance uh entropy
of sensory States these are probability
distributions
and Shannon talked about the uncertainty
of the receiver about the message sent
by the sender so if you want to extract
the same thing I suppose you can but but
it's important not to lose at least the
difference between what kind of object
are we applying to are we looking at
probability distributions are we looking
at Phase space are we looking at ideal
gas where are we at and we're just not
to say entropies entropies entropy
that's not the case I mean it's just a
formula but depending on the context
assumptions and and things it can be
very different
thanks Ollie and other
uh yes in regard to Alex's comments I
just wanted to mention the research of
people like Rudolph panel and Stefan
Cerner because uh for many years they've
been exploring this idea of different
conceptions of entropy and they've come
up with at least a dozen different
meanings for entropy and they've
formulated it in a kind of generalized
framework but at the same time they've
also devised uh
a way to somehow
classify them into equivalence classes
and to see whether one or more of those
conceptions of entropy can be
theoretically derived from uh from some
others or they're totally distinct and
different
um conceptions of entropy so yes I agree
that in some situations we need to be
more specific about what exactly we mean
by entropy and information uh
I mean based on the question or the
situation of Interest
thanks aval
ating the entrepreneur discussion I want
to emphasize that entrepates plnp so
it's a function for
probability distribution which is uh I
think I'm not sure what the term is
English but it's a measure of how big
something is in a space
and to get that you have to define a
space and in many cases it's
preservatory to decide what the space
you're looking at is for example you
talk I don't know if it was like say it
was like say someone talked about
uh entropy of fmri
well those are aggregate measurements of
General activity this is not the space
of all possible configuration and even
if I add something like the space of all
and to say functional configuration the
state in your own that reflect activity
this would be
another thing than the space of I don't
know Atomic configuration where the
specific atom are so
yeah you don't have a warranty that's
when you define entropy you define it on
a main full space that stopped given
so let's
I kind of think there is one entropy and
that's it and need some info constructs
but also we have to if we agree to that
then we can tell that we have to find it
it's not just given out there in the
data
well certainly being precise in the
formalism and in natural language for
what we mean by information and entropy
and all these terms
is pretty important I mean the course
we're in is physics as information
processing
but without an understanding of how
information is being meant here
or what measurements and Transformations
were were performing what informational
operations then
it it
um
is it
a non-sequitur
so how do we how do we go about
um clarifying
or understanding what kinds of
theoretical results in a given domain or
like what is shown on the timeline here
might apply to some other area
Just one thought
anyone else can raise their hands with
uh
a thought or a question
otherwise Andre you can um maybe
flip over to to select a few of the
submitted questions
cool could you zoom in
um with control plus a fair amount
thanks so everyone
um we really appreciate the submitted
questions we've been able to get 13
answered by Chris so far
and
um as with the transcripts of the
discussions and lectures the questions
and answers are going to be part of what
is published by the octave Journal so we
really encourage
basic questions Advanced questions just
there's no question that doesn't make
sense to submit
so under maybe just pick one question
that you think's interesting to begin
with and summarize uh Chris's response
and then everyone else is welcome to
kind of add some other thoughts on this
no
so I'm going to scroll up and down just
to sort of sample uh let me start with
the first two can you hear me well yep
uh since perhaps I think you submitted
this as a trial right is that is that
right yeah
so what is information about this time
um
here's Chris's response I guess everyone
has a chance to look at it now the one
if I am to summarize this the one thing
I've heard that you know it's personally
the one I like the most
um the answer at least as an adage to
summarize it is that information
um are differences that make a
difference this I might have heard from
Chris I might have heard from someone
else I don't remember
but that's one thing
now on to the question of what is time
and I guess this also addresses uh
Alex's question of what is entropy I
so I'll make a bigger point now uh what
is time this is partially addressed and
I guess the main thing I'll be doing
here is rather than look back look
forward into
what's to come in the course in
particular I'm thinking about
um
you know this these two papers uh and in
particular
[Music]
particular and I finally chat with with
Chris about this uh this picture over
here okay more
yeah
I'll get back to you in a bit but
basically this this also sort of like
kills two birds with a stone right this
picture and especially the text around
it and the title of this paper is the
physical meaning of the holographic
principle okay you guys can see here
archive 2020
2210 blah blah blah anyways
this addresses the notion of you know
the time on entropy because the the
point that's the claim that's made in
this paper is that these are local
Observer relative definitions and we can
uh
look into more detail around it but
basically
the coordinate ta time is an entropic
measure so it is non-decreasing and it
goes up with The Observer measuring uh
entropy in the system
because of the symmetry of the
definition the second law applies to
both so both of server and environment C
entropy increasing
in their environment and vice versa
anyways
from from this picture one gets that you
have this internal Circle time qrf so
this just is is a necessary artifact of
recording information into a memory
that's that's the claim made in the
paper
and that essentially induces the
passenger of time at least from the
perspective of the Observer
um it also I think Alexi was talking
about which I totally uh understand and
agree with different Notions of of
entropy now
I suppose as the the you know
I I would be the one to to like
definitions and so on
um but I but I do think it's it's it's
good to to have a certain amount of
flexibility
um so
I see the same as energy right like
there are different kinds of energy you
know there's energy mass equivalences
and
you know if you push it into Super
symmetry you can think of it as
equivalent as Force also
but I I do think there is some value in
being sloppy or intuitive about about
the notion so so the fact that you know
entropy yes there are different
definitions I I don't I don't see it
quite as a problem you know one can
explore here around this this page
there is a definition of you know local
entropic time and
yeah one can think of it as you know
face Pace or what can think of it as you
know coding Theory but it is at the end
of the day I do think it is true that
both of them are hinting at the same
direction just like you know you may
have different kinds of energy
but
um you know they're not unrelated
Concepts and and yeah I hope one day we
get very precise definitions about
everything but but for now I think it's
good to speculate
okay there's a question yeah Corby and
then anyone else on this
yeah quick question so I haven't read
that specific paper
but is there any work on
the frequency or the rate at which one
could read and write information on the
boundary
yes well I I don't I don't I can't think
of the the paper exactly but this is
lower bounded I think Chris talked about
it
if not in the last lecture I I think
I've seen a talk of him on YouTube it's
lower bounded by the uncertainty
principle right
um so so for instance uh plants Planck's
constant is in
units of action which is energy times
time right so Leonard's principle says
you need a certain amount of energy you
know to raise information
and
you have time right and then you have an
energy time uncertainty principle
putting those things together right you
have any minimum amount of action which
is you know literally the minimum uh the
action is measuring what I said earlier
right like differences that make a
difference the minimum difference that
you can make so the minimum difference
to
you know you raise a bit or rewrite it
on the boundary so to speak right
uh so yeah that would be given by the
uncertain relation energy times time
it's I don't know exactly the figure is
but it's obviously very small compared
to Everyday Life
got it and with is there work on the
upper bound like for example would it be
the number of degrees of freedom on
Boundary
no I don't think it's bonded from above
but but obviously you know then
we do want to buy it from above for
technological reasons if you wish but I
I think that is a an engineering problem
not not one of you know physics
um under a few few questions on this
figure
um
what are y and e
B the blue oval as Chris has pointed out
is going to consistently be the screen
the blanket and so we often associate
that with uh at least some blankets
include these information gathering
utilizing systems so what is happening
internal to the agent here what kind of
computation is happening and is this
something that is actually proposed to
be occurring
or is this a schematic or a map of how
we could think about something occurring
so
I think this question is going to be
better addressed by Chris himself
probably in the next lecture
um for now what I can say is I can
reiterate what I was trying to say
earlier which is that with these
addresses and you know these basic
measurement pictures so to speak is the
observer effect right like this notion
that you cannot observe something we
thought
without disturbing the environment so if
you then try to make sense of this by
constraining
you know from first principles Land
hours principle and so on uh basic
requirements on information processing
from the point of view of energy
then you get that this boundary
is constrained in some ways right this Y
is What's called the memory sector
meaning that
you don't just act on on the immediate
information that you perceive you may
also act on you know start that story
that you have perceived before
and then sure e the red part is what
you're perceiving right now the
environment uh but actually I don't know
if I have it in here
uh but this is further broken up into
other parts so not schematically here
let me try to find it over here
no I don't know actually bear with me
for a second I think you might be here
if that's the same picture
anyways I I'm not I don't want to waste
time by trying to find it but
back to the original picture
yeah sure you use what you're measuring
and again Chris will talk about this in
more detail yeah but from first
principle assumptions
they deduce that you're gonna have to
you know deploy your finite resources
for gathering information in clever ways
on the boundary right so you're gonna
have to deploy some resources for memory
some resources uh as a free energy uh as
a heat sink right so you're going to be
processing information so you're going
to be dumping you know so-called low
quality stuff into the environment
you're going to be dumping Heat
and then
other than the memory you're going to be
focusing on what's going on right now
in this environment and what I wanted to
say is that it can be further broken up
into what's called pointer and reference
sectors so you can imagine this
e-sector here has to be broken into
further sectors because then there's the
other first principle notion okay so
what does it mean to observe some
something the differences that make a
difference right so you can only there's
only information with context right
there is no information per se it's all
semantics right so you've only observe
things in context
so some things are going to have to stay
the same
namely you know reference States here
and some things are going to Bear right
so you can think of this as the gauge in
your car right obviously the circle
stays the same
right and that's your context so to
speak that's the with the you know
numbers in it they never go away they
stay the same but as you speed up around
the gauge is going to change and that's
how you know only in that context you
you can tell you're on speed when you're
driving a car
right
so anyways this is just a teacher for
things to come
you can go back to more questions then
what do you think I'll pick maybe two
two or three more over here
yeah pick another question or anyone
raising their hand or if anyone in the
live chat wants to write something I'll
read it
how about the wick rotation could you
summarize what the wick rotation is and
then State this question about it
so yeah that's a great question I knew
the answer but I wish I knew the answer
was better but unfortunately speaking
um the weak rotation is just so is Chris
said you know you take a quantity you
multiply by I
square root of negative one that amounts
to a 90 degree rotation in a complex
plane fine now that appears to be a
trick
and what it does effectively is take you
from quantum mechanics to
statistical mechanics roughly speaking
uh
now why it works that's
probably I mean I have no clue I don't
know the answer myself but now
when things appear to be a trick and
they get you something maybe there's
more to it than than what's you know
Apparent at first uh but I myself don't
know to know the answer it's a very good
question
uh but I I do think it may have to do
with the fact that
on the one hand Quantum and statistical
mechanics both are
talking about
um
constraints on information processing
maybe from different perspectives but
again that's just the speculation on my
I I don't know so it's maybe a way of
relating the two
did we just review just read Chris's
full answer to this read the question
and then Chris's full answer
foreign
space
[Music]
um
and then I'll I'll just read Chris's
answer then anyone please raise your
hand if you want to like add something
more on this he wrote in a sense yes
time is perpendicular to our three
dimensions of space matter and energy we
ourselves exist in time Wick is pointing
to the intimate relationship between how
we measure time and how we determine or
judge that something maintains its
identity Through Time IE stays the same
thing through a time to tell time by a
clock I have to be sure I'm looking at
the same clock set the same way
Etc we'll get to this in July and August
could you connect this under to some of
the um
semantic information flows
discussed in live stream 17 or any of
the other uh cone cocone diagrams from
the papers that you showed earlier
uh sure again I have to preface it by
saying that
I am working on understanding it myself
but
um just from you know
small
Email exchange that I had with Chris and
website in this paper
one can sort of see that it's related to
the picture I was showing earlier let me
this one right but let's scroll down a
little bit to page
to page 23 24 here they took out the
rotation again
uh
so
I think it has it has to do with uh at
least from what I heard from Chris gay
email has to this notion of local local
time
the definition of local time in this
observation picture
and you know the fact that you know
rotate 90 degrees
twice you get
the opposite sign basically right so
uh the local time
effectively that's going to ensure that
that the picture is symmetric and that
you know
the flow is going to be opposite in in
the direction uh towards the The
Observer and towards the environment
okay Alexi then anyone else raising
their hands
I I am struggling to understand and part
of my difficulty bear with me ever being
so uh kind of but I remember Sean
Carroll's uh lecture on time in
different versions of physics and it
took a whole hour so are we talking
Newtonian time which is universally the
same I would talk in relative time uh
you know philosophically are we talking
about people who believe that only
present here and now is real while
future and past do not exist you know so
when we say time is perpendicular too my
my sense is that just like Chris
mentioned and what you were Reinventing
the time we're creating a new definition
by calling it the same word we're all
familiar with and that creates some
dissonance where I I I just think that
maybe we need to kind of say that this
is something new and if it's not
something new then which version of the
time are we talking about Einstein
Newtonian or whatever you know it's a
simple question if we before we say it's
perpendicular do people agree that
future is uh real or not you know
again speculation
um neither here nor then
if we take Chris seriously that
communication is an ontological primary
and that rather than
putting Communications protocols in some
sort of time
Newtonian time Einstein time these are
these different time Concepts
these different scaffolds that then
communication gets inscribed within or
stretched within but if we start with a
topological understanding of
communication rather than a geometric
understanding of space-time
so the topology of the blanket and the
observer in their sensorium
then different kinds of cognitive agents
ranging from what we would call
non-living to what we could call living
they depending on their cognitive
sophistication are able to create or
project different time Concepts
time Concepts that are not useful will
lead to their own material dissolution
the failure to maintain that kind of
cognitive sophistication which requires
um not just information gathering
utilization but also energy Gathering
and utilization
and so when you have multiple agents who
are um whether you conceptualize them as
within a message passing relationship
and having uh no surprise on the clock
on the wall
then they're like in a local time
synchrony
but the primary case is one entity
engaging with its sensorium and its
self-modeling time
in terms of progression
and so these previous time Concepts and
these different attempts to kind of
survey the structure of space-time
reflect different cognitive models
that cognitive agents have proposed
for time
and that communication actually like
takes ontological Primacy over all of
these ramified
um potentially overlapping potentially
non-overlapping time Concepts
but their Downstream of Agents cognitive
models
not vice versa
I'm not sure it's how I interpreted what
Chris said about communication being an
ontological primary though
so if we take one instance of a covid-19
virus a single kind of instance right
it's got no memory and no ability to
plan
is there a local time for that virus
versus you know Humanity observing how
the virus spreads across the globe and
you know we have agents with memory and
planning you know so
is there a time relative to a single
Photon you know I I just I mean it's
it's my hunch is that there's a
possibility that we're simply inventing
something brand new and defining it
brand new and I just they draw in
parallel back to all these other times
you know I understand the effort but
it's it's just
um
is it is that a brand new time is it
some other kind of time I don't know
so I I understand Alex's question uh and
I think it's sort of related to at least
morally speaking to your concern about
different kinds of entropy right
um
and what I can say is that also we have
Gladys Brook uh Marciano and so on they
have this
um recent paper on Quantum error
correction
uh so uh I have yet to read it and take
a closer look but here they talk about
space time right
and my punch
to address Alex's question is that if
you could sort of recover the more
familiar Notions of time
in a correspondence principle sort of
way you know by taking some you know
Newtonian limit or H bar goes to zero or
speed of light was infinity and so on uh
that would be very satisfactory sure
they may be doing a new thing
but you know recording old stuff and
then you think it's a good sanity check
and so long as we can see that being
worked out I think I'd be very happy
and just to the virus point I would
argue that viruses through their
physical engagement they do have memory
but they don't necessarily have the
awareness
or a metacognition on that memory
except as granted by intergenerational
evolutionary type pressure
but they do have past events
modifying them within some
set of possibilities
so
they're just being them
and their internal time is is on
there isn't a cognitive Observer
necessarily
in terms of like a narrative I
I am watching the clock
but they do change
but it's certainly very provocative if
this is not or we could also look to
Kronos and Kairos
and about the the relationship of time
and timeliness and agentic time
so I think there's and then at this
point are we stretching just this one
four-letter word too far
just like we brought up with information
entropy
I mean can we think about these as kind
of like continents
and then just if someone said I visited
this continent you know that you need to
specify a lot more
or what
granularity are these topics Corby and
then anyone else raising their hands
yeah on this topic
before a Markov blanket you have a
transition Matrix my question is how do
you how are you allowed to increment
that transition Matrix to calculate a
future State like what does that mean in
terms of time uh are you only allowed to
increment it by like the lower bound
time which is H over
oh and KBT
does that question make sense
I'll give a first pass on this we have
discrete time and continuous time models
in active inference
for a discrete time model where you have
the B transition Matrix
then the choice of delta T is a
modeler's decision and we talked about
this a lot in live stream 52 on
accelerated optimization there's some
delta T that's like going to get you the
most accelerated optimization if you
have too small of delta T then you're
either oversampling or you're maybe even
physically unrealistic like you pointed
to or if you have some long delta T
you're also not making an informative
simulation
in the discrete time case where you're
explicitly making time steps contrast
with the continuous time generative
model where we're doing more of a Taylor
series expansion on the generalized
coordinates at which point delta T is
not required you're merely just taking
an extended approximation from a given
snapshot and so delta T doesn't even
come into play
got it okay that makes sense
I don't know how it ties into time but
it helps clarify a little bit
okay anyone else can raise their hand or
um Andre kind of
maybe one more question or one more
topic from a paper just what's one more
puzzle piece
that you think
gives us a first coat of paints
from
questions submitted or from one of these
papers that you have up
what's something that that helps us
connect the dots a little bit
uh so I don't I don't think I have a
good answer let me look at the questions
again
uh
but regarding time I'll just reiterate
uh what I said I say record these
questions which is that I believe
Chris will address it
in in this bit I I don't know if you can
see what I'm sharing on the screen but
the paper will start all these
communication protocols blah blah blah
from March of this year
uh does talk about space-time
it's a Quantum uh error correction code
and to me personally it'd be nice to see
if that can be if more familiar Notions
of time such as
special relativity can be recovered past
limits in correspondence principles
um
yeah do you want me to say anything else
if anyone could even just summarize like
what what would these what are these
codes referring to
or how are are these codes one and the
same as communication protocols
or are they related to the blanket and
the the heat that was being output as
waste
What will what will these codes allow us
to do better if we understood them more
I don't know that I can answer that
right now I don't I don't think they
understand the question
um yeah I I just don't know
sorry
Terry and then anyone else raising their
hands
um I I'm not a physicist I don't
understand maths at all
M but what attracted me to this um idea
of physics is information processing is
that
um
it feels like at a base level
the whatever the X on normal external
status it could be perceived as
made up of information you know we we
kind of think of ourselves living in a
particular universe but you know at a
base level there are these and stop me
if I'm just talking 14 year old nonsense
here but you know that there's there's
no Quantum Fields they feel like
informational fields
and
um
that
the the the concept of of physics is
purely information
that we then interpret
as a physical Universe which we inhabit
because we can't see beyond our Markov
blanket
um
I find this a really exciting
idea that
as a that whenever you start to think of
the um surprisal as the
um variational free energy between you
know sort of your your prior and your
posterior if you start to think of that
variational free energy not as energy
but as an information Gap so that if you
see the energy as actual you know
because energy when you think of energy
in physics terms it's kind of this
magical thing that does that allows work
to happen or you know but but what is it
you know we've got a a term for it and
we've got we've got we've got a you know
we there's a jewels you know or whatever
you know but but what does it mean it
has this magical property but if you
think of it as an information
um then it starts to make sense so
variational free energy starts to be
seen as a difference in information
between what you uh your your prior and
your exterior
so whenever you start to think about
time time is this conceptual metric that
we use
almost because we have memory and
um I I wonder if we are getting uh
trapped in this semantics and all I have
is English because I don't understand
the maths really but um we we you know
you guys come in here and you do
understand the maths and then you
convert it into English which I think I
understand and then I can think of it
like a kid in a sweaty shop or a physics
class at the 14 years of age
I don't really know what I'm saying I
don't know what I'm saying but at a
fundamental level everything that we're
talking about is in for I I I can
understand this as information and I'm
excited to see how things develop what
are your thoughts on this craziness
so many uh great pieces in there
physics as information processing
what is it that actually allows the
steam engine to run and
the ball to move
that kind of physics
and then as the timeline laid out also
occurring during a period of immense
technology and and apparatus development
and and digitization all of this and
unconventional Computing as well
it's almost like this uh materialist
dualism
that instead of with with mind and body
that there was some kind of dualism
between the types of forces and energies
and ways of thinking about what made the
steam engine work and then what makes a
computer work
and so you'd understand how the computer
could fall off a cliff but then you
wouldn't necessarily be able to use that
exact kind of mechanics and physics and
Dynamics to study like how the computer
operated but you could say it weighed 11
pounds
and so I think the the provocation and
then which is as you hinted towards um
first off would be awesome to have a
natural language math and graphical
synthesis the triple play
but also then to use a common approach
to understanding this
and what wasn't working or is not
proposed to work is trying to fit
information
into that non-cognitive universe
but rather if we take the cognitive
Primacy of communication
then
all of these forces as inferred by the
sensorium which is all we're ever going
to have totally the most valid first
principles constraint to make
maybe then we'll be able to have a lot
more synthesis about even how steam
engines work
when we understand that word Bound in
that inference by our sensorium and all
that comes along with that in the
variational free energy bounding
surprise on our generative model
um Dean
um I'm gonna I'm gonna come at this from
the position of a 14 year old lens
because I don't think there's anything
unique about that
um I think on
most basic level
what I took away from Chris's lecture
was that there are that there's
information processing of at least two
types uh one is
figuring it out as in figure five or any
of these other figures that are up on
the screen right now or
anything that stabilizes
the world around us I think examples
have come up in this conversation
already of apology or geometry
there's a second type of information
processing which is outing the figure
type of information which is searching
and I think Lexi used the expression
which time
are we talking about
so these two types of processes are
quite different if you do a comparative
analysis of the two
you have information practicing
and you have to have both of the
processes to really get a sense
conceptually of what it is
the communication is really talking
about
if you're our information practicing
your way finding
until you collapse to something we might
describe in a verb tense as wave found
it's in the quantizing of that
invariance state that vast ocean if you
want to think of it metaphorically oh to
all
all Horizons on the manifold into a
variant or a nuanced or a discretized or
an orientation type of State
where all of a sudden things like
currents and temperature ships and even
think things that we've applied labels
to like entropy and a transition Matrix
suddenly appear out of the seam and
nothingness or the invariance so
that's not the math
but that's kind of stepping back and
saying what is the math
trying to say I think it boils down to
the comparative analysis
and then I think I'm hoping that in the
coming lectures Chris starts opening
that up and doing kind of the back and
forth between the two types of of
figuring it out
and Outing the figures because I think
when both are
are part of the conversation that's when
we start to get a sense of what's really
going on
thank you
in this sort of closing sessions
especially if anyone hasn't um added
anything please
feel free to give any
last Reflections or questions arising
so first as many people as would like
can reflect that way
um and then after every hand has been
addressed
then uh Ander if you could just give us
a kind of look ahead so Avil first then
anyone else with just where does this
discussion take us
and what do you want to continue to to
learn more about FL
oh uh so two things first if I walk out
of here without understanding what is
England I won't be disappointed
and uh I I don't actually expect it to
happen in like 12 hours that seems like
it's something but more uh seriously I
was a career I can I can agree with that
difficulty that there is Unity between
like physical structure and
communication protocols
but and that communication Protocols are
quantum reference frame kind of
individuate physical States individuate
meaningful measurement outcome that our
array file as physical possibilities
but the question is then where do
communication protocols slash Quantum
reference frame come from like what are
the physical determinants that bring
about those things and uh that seems
like a question that could be addressed
at the conceptual level with this course
and I would like uh
I I saw the live stream 17.
so that did not help uh anyway
um
I would like to uh to other more grip
into that if we can just say to the
following courses thank you
thank you
anyone else especially if they haven't
added anything yet
want to give kind of a closing
thought
yeah there's a lot to learn and Chris
brings up a lot in his lecture even
though we've only had one it's one of
the denser hours
of
epistemic resourcing
that I've seen
and there's also all of these accessory
and Cutting Edge works that that Andre's
showing
so
um I'm really looking forward to how we
can continue to curate and improve the
questions that we have
so that the uncertainties in our
generative model that we have how would
this be useful what does this mean why
is this variable this way what is the
implication for that those are all the
great questions and let's just get them
inscribed on our classical documents
so that we can have other Quantum
cognitive agents reduce their
uncertainty
by looking at the responses
so with that
I wonder if you could just look ahead to
lecture two
and just like Point towards where we're
gonna be
going
uh yes so
so lecture two will I think from what I
hear from Chris is gonna start to
address
is uh
you know basic pathological aspects of
the content measurement so the the two
sources to look at would be
two papers mainly this one physical
meaning of the holographic principle I
this one's by far the most pedagogical
one so
if I had to if I had to suggest that
folks look at one it would be this one
it's very easy to read I think uh but
maybe for a bit more detail
there's the slightly older one and they
talk at length about corn cocoa and the
high grounds here
um
free energy principle for genetic
content systems and so I think that's
what's going to come in these two
lectures basically the main ideas Behind
These two papers
Anya that's all I have to say
all right well
thank you for all who joined this first
discussion
hope that it was
fun for you and for the audience
and
check out the course site for the
readings to get ahead of the second
lecture we'll all
watch the second lecture and come back
in about a month for the second
discussion everyone's welcome to join
and the website has the registration
information and so now that we've seen a
little bit of one way it can be
we may do something similar or we may do
something different for the second
discussion so thanks again everybody
see you later
foreign